<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	
	xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss"
	xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#"
	>

<channel>
	<title>The International Guild of Handhooking Rugmakers &#8211; The International Guild of Handhooking Rugmakers</title>
	<atom:link href="/tag/the-international-guild-of-handhooking-rugmakers/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/</link>
	<description>2022 - 2024 Niagara Falls, Ontario</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Thu, 24 Apr 2014 01:22:55 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-CA</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	

<image>
	<url>https://i0.wp.com/tighr.net/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/TIGHR-Logo.jpg?fit=32%2C32&#038;ssl=1</url>
	<title>The International Guild of Handhooking Rugmakers &#8211; The International Guild of Handhooking Rugmakers</title>
	<link>/</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
<site xmlns="com-wordpress:feed-additions:1">203849854</site>	<item>
		<title>What&#8217;s in a Name? a lifestyle? hobby? traditions? Contemporary?</title>
		<link>/2014/04/23/whats-in-a-name-a-lifestyle-hobby-traditions-contemporary/</link>
					<comments>/2014/04/23/whats-in-a-name-a-lifestyle-hobby-traditions-contemporary/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[tighr10]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 23 Apr 2014 22:12:11 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[international membership rug hooking]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[rug hooking]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Rug Hooking Styles]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Australian Rug Hooking]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[contemporary rug hooking]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[international rug hooking]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[international rug hooking group]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[The International Guild of Handhooking Rugmakers]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Victoria British Columbia]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://tighr.connolley.co.uk/?p=1068</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Words influence the attitude one assumes when discussing their craft. Is it a profession, hobby, social/psychological/creative outlet? We are educating in casual conversation even with an initial title……. rugger, fiber artist, rug hooker, matter, hooker, textile artist, traditional rug hooker. Recently our international membership responded, many describing their mindset for the terminology: Susan Sutherland, Ontario, [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Words influence the attitude one assumes when discussing their craft. Is it a profession, hobby, social/psychological/creative outlet? We are educating in casual conversation even with an initial title……. rugger, fiber artist, rug hooker, matter, hooker, textile artist, traditional rug hooker. Recently our international membership responded, many describing their mindset for the terminology:</p>
<p><strong><span style="color:#ff0000;">Susan Sutherland, Ontario, Canada</span></strong><br />
“If someone asks me what I do, I generally say I’m a<strong> fibre artist</strong> and I use traditional rug hooking as my preferred method of creating my art. If I want to have someone ‘stop in their tracks’ I tell them first I’m a “hooker”, and then I qualify it and say I’m a fibre artist and I use traditional rug hooking methods that our pioneer mothers did.</p>
<p>There is so much misconception about rug hooking with strips of fabric that I find I’m always clarifying what I do. I sometimes say ‘I don’t knot nor do I use short pieces of wool yarn’, especially if someone says ‘Oh yes, I did that when I was a child or in school’. Most of those who say this in Canada are remembering latch hooking.”<br />
<strong><span style="color:#0000ff;">Fritz Mitnick, Pennsylvania, USA</span></strong><br />
“I imagine most Americans say &#8220;<strong>I am a rug hooker</strong>&#8220;. I do proddy also. I also thought about our guild name. I never say the full name. I say the international guild or the international guild of rug hookers. Maybe I should start doing it right!<br />
Of course my husband always introduces me saying, &#8220;This is Fritz. She is a hooker.&#8221;</p>
<p><strong><span style="color:#800080;">Judi Tompkins, Australia</span></strong><br />
“Obviously I&#8217;m a<strong> &#8220;hooker&#8221;</strong>&#8230;.and I usually explain that to be a great hooker means that I am a good stripper&#8230;..ah how I luv the ashen looked faces I see!  Clearly I am the crazed, white-haired ol&#8217; lady…. Sometimes &#8211; when I&#8217;m trying to be &#8220;nice&#8221; or &#8220;professional&#8221; I&#8217;ll ID myself as a &#8220;traditional fibre artist&#8221;&#8230;.which means I don&#8217;t fall into an immediate category of &#8220;hooker&#8221; (many think of latch hooking) and opens the dialog about the spectrum of how these 3 words might be defined/applied.”</p>
<p><strong><span style="color:#ff0000;">Heide Brown, British Columbia, Canada</span></strong><br />
“I say “I’m <strong>a Hooker</strong>.” Which always gets giggles or weird looks till someone, me if I’m alone, qualifies the term to — “Rug-hooker.”<br />
I like “Rugger”  — my friend here calls herself a “Matter” and our weekly hook group “Monday Matters”. (NOTE: TIGHR’s newsletter is called “Hooking Matters”)</p>
<p><strong><span style="color:#008000;">Jenni Stuart-Anderson, Herefordshire, UK</span></strong><br />
“I call myself <strong>a rag rug maker</strong> or designer/maker depending on where it is.<br />
I have not heard the term “rugger” here in UK, maybe rug maker but that could be a weaver. Of course everyone sniggers when I say hooker, even if the term is American.”</p>
<p><strong><span style="color:#ff0000;">Lynne Hunt, British Columbia, Canada<br />
</span></strong><span style="color:#ff0000;"><span style="color:#000000;">&#8220;I think we all struggle with the term hooker. I find here on the Coast most folks think of latch hooking and the shag rugs of the seventies. I tell people I am <strong>a fibre artist</strong> (gulp). It is a fine art practised at many levels. Whether you design your own work or work with the designs of others, there is so much more in what we do. I tell people I make mats, for the wall, the floor, chairs, tables- only limited by your imagination. I explain that I use a backing of burlap or linen, strips of fibre, mostly wool, new and recycled and a hook similar to one used centuries ago. I explain that the process involves colour planning, maybe some dyeing and choosing textures and materials for your work.</span></span><span style="color:#ff0000;"><br />
</span><span style="color:#ff0000;"><span style="color:#000000;">So I am <strong>a mat maker</strong> in the tradition of our pioneer sisters, creating something functional and beautiful.&#8221;</span></span><strong><span style="color:#ff0000;"><br />
</span></strong></p>
<p><strong><span style="color:#0000ff;">Elizabeth Soderholm, Virginia, USA</span></strong><br />
“My husband loves that I call myself <strong>a hooker</strong> and it always grabs folks&#8217; attention.  Gives me a chance to talk about this wonderful fibre/fiber art.  My boss (who is from Mississippi) will ask me on a Friday, in his lovely Southern drawl, &#8220;You goin&#8217; hookin&#8217; this weekend?&#8221;  It&#8217;s probably the best way to bring attention to our craft outside of schlepping our rugs and other projects around with us.”</p>
<p><strong><span style="color:#0000ff;">Liz Alpert Fay, Connecticut, USA</span></strong><br />
“I call myself : <strong>a textile artist</strong> or sometimes just <strong>an artist</strong>.<br />
I make: hand hooked rugs and mixed media sculpture.”</p>
<p><strong><span style="color:#0000ff;">Sarah Province, Maryland, USA</span></strong><br />
“I call myself a<strong> &#8220;fiber artist&#8221;</strong> and our medium &#8220;hooked fiber art&#8221;.</p>
<p><strong><span style="color:#ff0000;">Jane LeBaron, British Columbia, Canada</span></strong><br />
“I variously call myself a<strong> hooker and braider, a quilter</strong> and bookbinder and general <strong>fibre freak</strong>. I am fully confident that upon one brief look at me people understand my intended context in use of the term &#8220;hooker&#8221;&#8230;</p>
<p><strong><span style="color:#ff0000;">Rachelle Leblanc, Alberta, Canada</span></strong><br />
“I tell them that I am <strong>a fiber artist</strong> and I make fiber hookings.”</p>
<p><strong><span style="color:#0000ff;">Mary Watson, Washington,USA</span></strong><br />
“I say, &#8220;I&#8217;m a <strong>fibre artist</strong> and paint with wool”.</p>
<p><strong><span style="color:#0000ff;">Dianne Tobias, California, USA</span></strong><br />
“Since I came to hooking through braiding I introduce myself as <strong>a fiber artist</strong> then say I am a braider and a rug hooker. That seems to somewhat limit the usual jokes!”</p>
<p><strong><span style="color:#ff0000;">Sheila Stewart, British Columbia, Canada</span></strong><br />
“I use the term<strong> fibre artis</strong>t and then say I am a rug hooker.”</p>
<p><strong><span style="color:#0000ff;">Linda Rae Coughlin, New Jersey, USA</span></strong><br />
“I tend to work with this statement, the response changes depending on who I am speaking with, i.e. fellow artist vs. a layperson.<br />
I am<strong> an artist</strong> whose medium is textile. I create with the technique of rug hooking/stitching using recycled clothing and materials.”</p>
<p>During the <a title="2009 Louisville, KY USA" href="///our-triennials/2009-louisville-ky-usa/">2009 Tri-Ennial</a> held in Louisville, Kentucky, USA we asked attendees the terminology they used to describe favorite fiber techniques. <strong><span style="color:#800080;">Miriam Miller</span></strong>, an Australian is a<strong> rugger</strong> and spinner; <span style="color:#0000ff;">Susan Feller</span> West Virginia, USA a fiber artist specializing in rugmaking techniques; <span style="color:#0000ff;">Kim Dubay</span>, Maine USA fiber artist; <span style="color:#800080;">Jacqui Thomson</span>, Australia a rugger and spinner; <span style="color:#ff0000;">Iris Simpson</span>, Ontario Canada a Hooker; <span style="color:#ff0000;">Yvonne Muntwyler,</span> Ontario Canada a Fiber Artist in rughooking medium.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/2014/04/23/whats-in-a-name-a-lifestyle-hobby-traditions-contemporary/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
		<post-id xmlns="com-wordpress:feed-additions:1">1068</post-id>	</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
